Guide to the Bernhard Knollenberg Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Bernhard Knollenberg collection
1560-1943
MS 26
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8.75
(15 boxes, 2 folios)
Correspondence, diaries, manuscripts of writings, narratives, biographical sketches, documents, reports, addresses, deeds, tax receipts, printed material, and other papers, relating to early American colonial settlement, the American Revolution, settlement of the West, slavery, the Civil War, Spanish-American War, women's suffrage, and various political questions. Includes circa 100 letters (1838-1855) to Alvah Hunt, of Greene, Chenango Co, N.Y, describing current political issues, especially Whig politics, from Millard Fillmore, Hamilton Fish, Horace Greeley, Washington Hunt, William H. Seward, and Thurlow Weed; 171 letters written by Homer Sackett Curtiss to members of his family during his Civil War service in the 2nd Connecticut Volunteer Regiment, Heavy Artillery; papers of George Panton, loyalist, of New York, containing letters from Daniel Batwell, Thomas Bradbury Chandler, other loyalist Anglican ministers who escaped to England during the Revolution, and others interested in the Church of England in America; 35 letters and documents (1779-1804) by and relating to Nathanael Greene; correspondence, deeds, and tax receipts, relating to Joel Barlow and the Ohio Company; 2 volumes of letters and papers by François Alexandre-Frederick La Rochefoucauld Liancourt; correspondence and writings of Seth Reynolds; and diaries of Alfred Brammer, English workman.
Knollenberg, Bernhard, 1892-1973
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts from Bernhard Knollenberg from 1939
Existence and Location of Copies
Correspondence to George Panton is available on microfilm (circa 125 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM199
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Correspondence, 1560, 1622-1942. II. General File, 1747-1827, 1858-1868, 1901-1940.
Scope and Contents
The Bernhard Knollenberg Collection comprises original and copied manuscripts of American historical interest which were collected by the former Yale University Librarian in connection with his historical studies and presented to the Yale University Library in 31 accessions since 1939. Covering the entire span of American history, the collection is of major importance for the Colonial, Early National and Ante-Bellum Periods and is frequently consulted by the leading scholars of these periods. The typed and photostatic copies of manuscripts were obtained from many libraries and historical societies and from private collections.
Bernhard Knollenberg (b. 1892) was University Librarian from 1938 to 1945 and Lecturer on the Law of Taxation during the academic year 1941-1942. A student of law and history, he held the following government posts: senior deputy administrator, Lend Lease Administration, 1943-1944; division deputy, Office of Strategic Services, 1944-1945; and, United States Commissioner for the North-West Atlantic Fisheries, 1950-1958. Mr. Knollenberg was the recipient of five academic degrees: B.A. Earlham, 1912; M.A. Harvard, 1914; LL.B. Harvard, 1916; Honorary M.A. Yale, 1939; and LL.D. Earlham, 1944. The following books by Mr. Knollenberg as well as a number of journal articles were based in whole or in part on the manuscripts in the collection: Washington and the Revolution: A Reappraisal, 1940; Whitewater Valley, 1946; Samuel Ward, 1952; Origin of the American Revolution, 1960; and George Washington: The Virginia Period, 1964.
The manuscripts and copies are arranged in chronological order in 1220 folders (15 document boxes) and are individually foldered and described. Most of the items are individually catalogued in the Union and Departmental Manuscript Catalogues. The collection was established with the gift of the Alvah Hunt Papers in 1939. Over 100 letters written during the period 1838-1855 to Alvah Hunt of Greene, Chenango County, New York describe the political issues of the time, especially Whig politics. The principal correspondents include Hamilton Fish, Horace Greeley, William H. Seward, and Thurlow Weed. Other groups of papers of interest are listed below:
1. The Leffingwell Collection of manuscripts at the New Haven Colony Historical Society. Gift, 1942. Photostats.
2. The George Panton Papers which were presented to the Reverend Dr. Chorley by the Bishop and the Synod of the Diocese of Aberdeen and Orkney in 1934 and given to the Library in 1940. The letters are from Anglican ministers who were Loyalists and who escaped to England during the Revolution. A few are from men who were never in America, but were deeply interested in the Church of England in America. The two principal correspondents are Daniel Batwell and Thomas Bradbury Chandler. Chandler graduated from Yale in 1745 (see Dexter's Yale Biographies and Annals, 1701-1745 ), moved to England in 1775 and returned to America in 1785. He was an important figure in the Anglican Church in America. George Panton, according to Sabine's American Loyalists, was in New York in 1783 and was one of the 55 Loyalists who petitioned for lands in Nova Scotia at that time.
3. Homer Sackett Curtiss Papers, consisting of 171 letters written to members of the Curtiss Family during his Civil War service in the 2nd Connecticut Volunteer Regiment, Heavy Artillery. Gift, 1939.
4. Nathanel Greene Papers, including 35 original letters and documents by and relating to General Greene, 1779-1804. Gifts, 1943, 1944.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Yale University librarian (1938-1945); administrator in the Lend Lease Administration (1943-1944), Office of Strategic Services (1944-1945); U.S. Commissioner for the North-West Atlantic Fisheries (1950-1958).
American loyalists; Clergy; New York (State); New York (State) -- Politics and government; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; United States -- Politics and government -- 1783-1865; Worksop (Nottinghamshire); Deeds; Diaries; Librarians; Curtiss, Homer Sackett; Greene, Nathanael, 1742-1786; Hunt, Alvah; Knollenberg, Bernhard, 1892-1973; Panton, George; Connecticut. Militia. Regiment, 19th (1775-1777); United States. Army. Connecticut Infantry Regiment, 2nd; United States. Army. Connecticut Infantry Regiment, 7th (1861-1865); Whig Party (N.Y.)
- Correspondence (Chronological), 1560-1943; Series I; 5.5 linear feet (13 Boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains letters, manuscripts, documents, reports, printed material and photostatic copies of original material. The folders are arranged chronologically, with undated material arranged alphabetically by author's name at the end of the series.
  Topics covered include early colonial settlement, the American Revolution, slavery, The Ohio Company, the Civil War, the Spanish-American War, woman suffrage, and various political questions in the individual states and the nation as a whole. Many important historical names are found, including George Washington, John Adams, John Quincy Adams, Benedict Arnold, Paul Revere, Marquis de Lafayette, Horatio Gates, John Hancock, John Jay, Philip Schuyler, Thomas Paine, Anthony Wayne, Eli Whitney, Henry Knox, Nathanel Greene, John C. Fremont, John C. Calhoun, Daniel Webster, Benjamin Harrison, Robert Morris, Dorothea Dix, Susan B. Anthony, John Gibson Lockhart, John Singer Sargent, Edward Everett, Lewis Cass, William Sherman, E.C. Agassiz, James C. Dana, Augustus Saint-Gaudens, Theodore Roosevelt, Franklin Roosevelt, Jay Norwood Darling, and Charles Beard.
  A large number of letters are from Homer Sackett Curtiss, a Civil War soldier, to his family. Another group of letters are to Alvah Hunt, New York political figure, from William Seward, Governor Hamilton Fish, Thurlow Weed, Daniel Webster, Millard Fillmore, and Washington Hunt. A third voluminous mass of the series consists of material such as deeds, tax receipts, and correspondence pertaining to Joel Barlow and his dealings with the Ohio Company.
  Various narrative accounts and diaries are found in the series. These cover settlement of the West and biographical sketches of War heroes and frontiersmen.
  See Also: Series II for writings which complement correspondence found in Series I.
  - ALS, Maximilian (King of Bohemia); "To Whom It May Concern" - grant passage to carrier ? Vienna, 1560 August 5 (Box 16)
  - ALS, Leopold V, Archduke of Austria (1586-1683), to The Duke of Tuscany; requesting that Angelo Vettori be given a governor's job by the Duke, 1622 February 20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - A Copy of an Act of Parliament during the first year of the reign of James I concerning the poor; copied by Ralph Hopton, 1631 January 14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - ALS, Emperor Ferdinand III to the Mayor and Council of the town of Fridtberg answering their plea remove their contributions to his army. The Emperor urges them to continue contributing the necessary support, 1643 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Copy of document attesting that all undivided land after the second division in the town of Haverhill shall remain in the common possession of all towns people. Copy by Mitchel Sewall Clev, 1651 December 16 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Testament concerning a piece of land and what it contained; Thomas Danforth, Recorder. Language may bar co-mixture of Low German and English, 1652 August 7 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - A funeral sermon preached in Madrid at the interment of Richard Hanshaw, His Majesty's ambassador there by Dr. Bagshaw, 1666 July 4 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Deed of Hezekiah Williss of Hartford, Connecticut; deeded land to John Camp of Hartford in return for the indenture of the said Camp, Indenture: 1672 July 2 Deed:1697 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - ALS, Will Trumbull to Richard Bulstrode from Paris; concerns the conditions of Dutch in Paris and talk of the treaty between Spain and France, 1686 June 24 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Proclamation from the proprietors of East New Jersey to their settlers; that Lewis Morris has been given a grant of land to use to obtain naval stores for 6 pounds rent per year, 1703 April 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - ALS, Admiral Sir George Byng (1663-1733) sent from Port Mahon to Mr. Craggs; tells of reading for sea, 1709 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - ALS, Robert Hunter to Lewis Morris; thanks Morris for papers sent and asks him to fill in for him in a business deal, 1711 April 28 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - ALS, Rev. John Davenport (Stamford, Conn.) to Rev. Stephen Williams, (Springfield); tells of supplies going up river from Davenport to Williams, 1718 June 3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - ALS, Louis XV (France) to Monsieur Pucelli; requests absence from People's Assembly, 1718 June 23 (Box 16)
  - ALS, Jonathan Belcher (Governor of Mass.), to Rev. Nathaniel Chauncy (of Durham, Conn.); describes goods and a bill sent by Belcher to Chauncy. Boston, 1725 July 26 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - ALS, Lord Barrington to Lord Auson; recommending Captains Craven and Barker to Lord Auson's protection, 1727 August 19 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - ALS, Earl of Sandwich to (?); urging that Mr. Robbins, who had written an excellent treatise on gunnery, be allowed to go to the seige of Bergen op Zoom and subsequent seiges to put theory into practice, 1727 August 31 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - ALS, Franz III, Duke of Lorraine, to Archbishop of Trier; message of the death of the Archbishop's father carried by the Marquis de Lambertye. Letter in German with typed transcription and translation, 1730 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - ALS, Indenture certificate between John D. Osborn and various citizens of Albany, 1730 September 24 (Box 16)
  - Rent of land by James Rickets (Prince William County, Virginia) to George Mason (Charles County, Maryland) for 20 pounds, 1732 August 17 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - ALS, Daniel Dulany to Charles Carrole; asking Carrole to survey the south side of Dulany's land, 1737 February 4 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - ADS, Frederick the Great of Prussia, appointing Johann Christian Friedel "Adjunctus Fisc.", describing the duties, responsibilities, limits, and pay of said office. In German with transcription and translation, 1742 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - ALS, Barrington to (?); asking for a transfer of Barrington's brother from the ship Bellona to another vessel, 1747 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - ALS, Jacob Wendell (Oliver Wendell Holmes' grandfather) to Capt. Michael Butler; requesting that Butler pay the bills due to Jacob Wendall, Jr, 1754 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - ADS, Robert Morris to Nicholas Scull (Surveyor General of Penn.), authorizing the survey of 25 acres in Berkshire County for Charles Korn, 1775 March 19 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - ALS, C.V. Livingston to Robert Morris (Lieutenant Governor and C. in C. of Penn.); concerning the arrival of Col. Dunbar and two regiments of troops and the necessity of procuring supplies and transportation of the troops, 1755 August 14 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - ALS, Robert Hunter Morris to (?); concerns the disbanding of provincial troops and the state of affairs in Penn. Mention of Franklin, recto p. 2, 1755 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - AL, [Robert H. Morris?] to William Allen; concerning the way to stop the meeting and protests of the people of Lanchester County, 1756 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - ALS, (?) to Miss Lake; chronicle describing America, 1757 May (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - ALS, Duke of Newcastle to (?); concerning the sale of property. Newcastle felt that he had been cheated in sale and asked his friend to bring the matter to the attorney general, 1757 August 2 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - ALS, Duke of Halifax to (?); concerning a Mr. Lowry and a dispute over land that he bought or claimed, 1759 March 17 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - ALS, Rev. Soloman Williams to Rev. Eliphalet Williams of Hartford with a cure recipe for Eliphalet's sore leg; also has family news, 1761 March 6 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - ALS, Horatio Sharpe, Governor of Maryland, to the Commissioners of paper currency calling for an accounting of loans due, 1762 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - ALS, H. Moore to CO; discusses the removal of his household from Jamaica to London for health reasons, 1763 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Account page from a doctor's book, showing the debit of Enoch Parker, 1763 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - ALS, Hardwicke to (?); discussing the islands and lands that England owns because of the Definitive Treaty, 1764 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Cash record of William Dabney Ambler, 1764-1765 (Box 16)
  - AL, From the King (George III) concerning the duties of a Mr.Ellis on the King's business, 1765 March 23 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - List of debits and credits signed by Benedict Arnold, 1765 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - ALS, George Grenville to Fessey; discussing the purchase of an estate in Westcoate Field, 1765 November 9 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - List of Commissioners and Officers of His Majesty's customs, 1765 (Box 17)
  - AL, (John Hancock) to Richard Lawler thanking him for his help and asking Lawler to hold prosecution of Mather and Parsons Company, 1766 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Bill signed by Benedict Arnold against Richard Ewin, 1766 December 1 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Negotiable note from Dudley Woodbridge to Matthew Barns on Mr. Joseph Bently, 1766 December 24 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - List of regimental officers of Massachusetts photostatic copy, 1767 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - ADS, Roger Sherman; list of debts and assets signed by Benedict Arnold [photostat], 1767 May 5 (Box 16)
  - ALD William Lee to Robert Caster, 1769 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 46A)
  - List of debits and credit signed by Benedict Arnold, 1769 July 25 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - ALS, Dr. J. MacKnight to Rev. George Panton; requesting that Panton look after some household goods until MacKnight gets resettled. Also photostat of same, 1769 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - ALS, Dr. J. MacKnight to Rev. George Panton; speaks of furniture moved and being shipped as well as his plans for the future. With photostatic copy, 1769 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - ALS, Dr. J. MacKnight to George Panton; discussing the possibility of sending sermon materials via manservant to MacKnight. With photostatic copy, 1769 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - ALS, J. MacKnight to George Panton; asking him to send a mare and a saddle horse from Jedburgh to Temple on Dec. 22. With photostat, 1769 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Petition from George Panton to J. MacKnight asking for a change of school location in Jedburgh and requesting that the school be made a boarding school. With photostat, Circa 1769 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Copy of the Boston Gazette and Country Journal, 1770 March 5, November 5 (Box 16)
  - Notice from James Duane, attorney to Cortlandt Skinner, attorney for the defendant, that trial will be Sept. 6 in the town of Perth Amboy, 1770 August 24 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Legal document signed by John Dickson concerning the estate of Robert Hunter Morris, one of the proprietors of East New Jersey, and the settlement of claims due that property, 1770 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - ALS, R. Trailly to George Panton; at the University of Edinburgh - promising Panton a letter of recommendation to the Bishop of London so that Panton could change his job situation. With photostat, 1770 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - ALS, Bishop James of Down to David Hume; concerning the ordination of George Panton as a priest in Scotland. Down asks for permission to be obtained from the Bishop of London, who is the proper Bishop of Scotland, to perform this consecration. With photostat, 1770 December 22 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - ALS, Bishop James of Down to George Sandy; concerning ordination of George Panton as priest if Panton can get dismissory letter from the Bishop of London. With photostat, 1770 December 22 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - ALS, Professor William Trail to George Panton; stating that he thought the Bishop of London would give the dismissory letter. With Photostat, 1771 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - ALS, Bishop James of Down to David Hume; stating that the dismissory letter had arrived and requesting George Panton to be present with testimonials on February 20. With Photostat, 1771 February 4 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - ALS, R. Traills to George Panton concerning letter to be delivered by Panton to the Bishop of Down and expressing regrets that Panton is leaving. With Photostat, 1771 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Cover of the ordination papers of George Panton signed by Bishop of Down, David Hume, D. Traill, Mr. Sandy, and Professor William Trail. With Photostat, 1771 February 20 (ca.) (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - ALS, J. MacKnight to George Panton mentioning the offer of the Bishop of Down to give Panton a place in Ireland and asking Panton to consider if the Bishop's offer and possible friendship might not come in handy in America. With Photostat, 1771 March 8 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Receipt for diploma of Master of Arts granted to George Panton. With Photostat, 1771 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - ALS, J. MacKnight to George Panton concerning the collection of debts owed to Panton. With Photostat, 1771 March 13 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - ALS, J. MacKnight to George Panton indicating that Panton trained under MacKnight and that MacKnight has sent him a general letter of recommendation. With Photostat, 1771 March 25 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Deed to a plot of ground in Duchess County, Mass. William Brown to David Doty, 1771 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Instructions to Thomas Hutchinson upon his appointment as Governor of Massachusetts. Photostat, 1771 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Instructions governing the laws of trade and navigation given to Thomas Hutchinson, Governor of Mass. Photostatic Copy, 1771 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - ADS, Deed for land, David Van Horne, Hugh Wallace, 1771 April 13 (Box 16)
  - Benedict Arnold's accounts of sales at the Bay of Honduras, 1771 December (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Invitation to dinner, Mr. Riddocks to George Panton. With Photostat. (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Contract between P. Smith and Benedict Arnold for the delivery of Red Stone to Arnold for 20 shillings per square foot. Photostat copy of original, 1772 January 23 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - ALS, Rev. D. Williams to Stephen Williams explaining why he cannot lend his horse to his father, 1772 June 4 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - ALS, Isaac Low to Jellis Fonda acknowledging the receipt of furs, asking Fonda to send some Pearl Ash to sell, 1772 June 26 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - ALS, George washington to (?), relating to the settlement of Col. Thomas Codvill's estate. Photostat copy of the original, 1772 July 3 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Contract between Benedict Arnold and P. Hezechiah Bassit Photostat copy of original. for construction of a house, 1772 July 9 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - ALS, John Thomas to Joseph Trumbull, letter of introduction of Mr. Cushman. Photostat copy of original, 1772 August 9 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - ALS, Richard Varick to Robert Yates asks for an answer in a legal case which concerns a Mr. Scott, 1773 June 10 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - ALS, Henry Quincy to son, discusses the son's sale of a vessel he had built, speaks of his own discredit, 1773 June 14 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - ALS, J. MacKnight to George Panton, congratulating him on becoming established. Speaks of educating his own sons and putting them into business. With photostat copy, 1773 June 20 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - ALS Vam White to Messers. G. J. Dickerson asking to extend his bill of credit 100 pounds until his vessels arrive, 1773 June 26 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Copy of AL to Committee of Correspondence in Boston from secretary James Nudien of Newburyport stating their actions in regard to the landing of East India tea, 1773 December 21 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - ALS, J. B. Chandler to George Panton concerning the affairs of Panton's missionary post in Trenton, N. J. with photostat copy, 1773 December 23 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - ALS, Sir Frederick Haldiman, governor of Canada, to Rev. William Smith thanking him for a pamphlet and information, 1774 February 12 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - ALS, LLL to Rebecca Woolsey expressing his love and devotion and a promise to see her and marry her in the spring, 1774 February 20 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - ALS, Adam Drummond (British statesman) to John Watts talk of the rebellion of Boston, use of threat of force, but not the use of force, 1774 June 12 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - ALS, Governor Sharpe of Maryland to John Ridout, asking Ridout to act as agent in a business deal in England, 1774 July 22 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - ALS, Adam Drummond, (British statesman) to John Watts speaks of family and trade, 1774 November 3 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - ALS, Turgot, Anne Robert Francis, (Finance minister under Louis XVI)-1727-1781- to Monsieur La Mothe, indicating that he had received his suggestions for agrarian reform and would use them at the proper time, 1774 November 3 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Account pages for Vessels Polly and Peggy kept by Benedict Arnold, 1774 November 15 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - ALS, L. Lloyd to Rebecca Woolsey, Lloyd tells his feelings of the impending revolution. Letter carries instructions to burn it after reading, 1774 November 24 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Deed from John Quintin to Joseph Shippen for a tract of land in Northumberland County, Penn, 1774 December 13 (Box 16)
  - ALS John Stevens to Col. Benedict Arnold at Fort Ticonderoga, contains intelligence of operations in New York State. Photostat copy of original, 1775 May 17 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Document signed by President John Hancock to George Washington, appointing him Commander-in-Chief of the United Colonies Army. Photostat copy of original, 1775 June 22 (Box 2, Folder 95)